O.K.
啊！
第一條條咩？
佢啲地夠平。
邊有啲什麼嘅？
係黃正議員。
好，好，好，好。
其實我要五點半嘅。
就把緊機會，把緊機會係，唔該曬。
負責機構傳訊嘅，跟住都有個別團體人士而家分別進場㗎啦。
其實上咧，亦都由於係今次比較破例地咁多撥款咧，所以我覺得係值得我哋討論下嘅。噉我哋都或者申請當局咧有機會嘅時候咧，就提封翻個文件咧，等我哋下次編排討論咧，好嘛？
有足夠法定人數，都係而家係法定時間。我哋誒開始會議。大家知道，我哋今日討論嘅係關於誒少數族裔嘅就業事項啦。噉我哋請有關官員進場先啦，同埋請有關嘅誒出席公眾人士都可以分別進場。唔該曬。
為咗方便誒觀看緊嘅觀眾咧，我哋今日嘅政府嘅代表咧有勞誒有勞工處副處長李寶兒女士啦，誒勞工處嘅助理處長許柏坤先生，勞工處高級勞工事務主任嚴麗羣女士嘅誒職業管理局嘅代表咧就係。
譚志傑教授啦，係佢哋嘅副執行幹事。跟住我哋有僱員才再培訓局嘅彭炳雄先生咧，就係佢哋嘅副行政總監，負責係培訓服務嘅。跟住我哋有建造業議會嘅朱賢廉先生咧，係助理院長，係負責培訓工作嘅。有鄭思凡女士咧，係經理，係。
或者我哋趁呢個時間咧，將本嚟我哋臨尾嘅項目咧，或者提提大家就就收到阿黃萬正議員嘅一封信件咧，要求就有關財政預算案嗰個撥款咧，就作出一個討論嘅。噉，我覺得同我哋嘅雖然話可能同誒財政預算案比較多係關係啲，不過同少數長問題都仍有關係，而。
咧，你話誒政府有機會嘅時候咧，就提供翻文件。喂，大佬唔好有機會喎，有機會次即係留翻，跟住下次開會之間嘅機會。係啊係啊，下下次希望下次嘅誒疫情影響到修正我嘅講法啦嚇。有機會就客氣啲講啫，其實機會即係時間上機會大啲。係佢即係佢醒定啲㗎啦，快脆脆嚇。
哎。
啊！
friends。
Good afternoon, Chairman, everyone.
不諳到我的資格。
After this bad experience, I kept finding job by myself and.
Mr. Bujold，你ready to speak？Yes. Right. Go ahead, please. Three minutes, please.
Sabah Katua. Sorry, my my pronunciation not perhaps correct, but you may now speak for three minutes, please.
我係非常失望，和疑惑關於議會在就業匹配上的能動性。
我係布爾達巴哈德。我係住喺香港十幾年。我係讀書喺印度，我係讀到大學，我係讀到博士。
在beginning，我searched and froze various kind of job in the school setting by myself， and had interviews in some of the application， however none of them was successful。
at the moment, I tried to approach the labour department in Sai Kung, since I was living in the Sai Kung at the time. The attitude of the staff was pretty apathetic.
好喺誒公眾人士在座期間咧，或者我提大家咧，就誒，我哋現場有大家都可能都慣熟我哋嘅設備㗎啦，有呢個誒收聽嘅服務啦。第一線係我哋嘅廣東話版本，二線英文版本，三線普羅話版本。睇嚟大家咧，將來將剛才一陣間發言時間，會會喺三分。
分鐘啦，而大家如果唔夠時間講嘅，或者有其他資料嘅，可以提最尾提供畀我哋秘書處嘅。誒，睇嚟大家在現場發言咧，不享有立法會權力特權條例所有嘅保障同豁免嘅。同樣道理咧，有關嘅文件都獲不獲豁免嘅。誒，另外咧就係提提大家咧，我哋有一個公眾人士須知咧，大家直上會見到呢。
就係告示啦。有關於我哋會議上嘅一啲嘅常規啊。好，冇其他問題嘅話咧，我哋馬上就邀請我哋在席嘅人士咧，就誒或者發言咧。我哋先請第一位嘅人士咧，就係誒。We now start the deputation and invite Mr.誒Pujo。
和只係想我填喺一個 formal form，和後，under my ears，calling them frequently and keep them asking about the progress of the job matching with my qualification. They tried to settle by only introducing construction works and restaurant that food and beverage jobs to me. It was not.
安教育中心。
設喺一個鄉鎮，密集人口由ethnic minorities。
later, I found a teacher job in a private school. Meanwhile, also taught in.
好 afternoon，我係從Hey Grip，一個青年關注組，聚焦於EM就業問題。
with my friends and did not provide appropriate help like interpretation service in order to solve language barrier.
I'm a Hongkonger and I do not speak Cantonese, at least not proficiently. But I'm fully proficient in English, which is the second de facto language.
，所以EM jobseekers can get access to the labour department's case management and intensive employment support services. The following elements have been included in the service.
Local English speakers like me aren't welcomed into the field. Still, I speak three languages. Wouldn't I, as a therapist, be a good resource for our linguistically diverse society?
Hong Kong is an international city. Having a workforce with diverse language abilities is one of the characteristics of an international city. And not speaking Cantonese or writing Chinese should not result in unemployment.
Recruitment support to foster effective labour employment communication of job experience. I hope that labour department will consider this plan and suggestion. Thank you very much. Thank you, Mr. Deputal. We will now invite Ms. Petal Iban Cow, please.
Based on the bad experience on my job matching and the inadequacy of interpretation service of Labour Department, I strongly urge the Labour Department to set up an EM placement division in designated employment centre for EM survey.
Up till now, my friends still face similar experience and difficulties like mine in finding appropriate job in labour department. In addition, one of my friends got an injury in work setting and sought help from labour department. They stopped communicating.
作為 bachelor student wanting to pursue clinical psychology， I'm being asked to rethink， and why？ Because the arranged placement opportunities are all for Chinese-speaking clientele， meanwhile， English-speaking therapists from overseas practice in private clinics， which majority of the EMs cannot even afford。
僱用案管員，其中一些有EM族裔背景，來與EM求職者進行深入的跟進，透過提供個案諮詢、探討他們的職業偏好、與他們的資格、經驗、興趣和抱負，提供有關當地文化的工作資訊。
有個proper curriculum。
reading or writing Chinese.
The task force we propose should also eradicate discrimination and illegitimate Chinese proficiency requirements by thorough screening.
Moreover, the courses are mostly in Cantonese or some are in English. So, if there are some EM who do not know Chinese and English, they cannot take the courses at all.
我可列舉數不勝數的工種，那並不需要實際上具備良好的中文能力，但允許我將這項工作交給特別指定的專責小組，以使這些工種變得可獲得。
We have to redefine what a Hongkonger means, and speaking Cantonese cannot be a criterion. It is hypocrisy to call yourself as being international while we are rejecting Hong Kong's ethnically different locals as 香港人.
Based on these problems, I want to suggest designated employment centres of EMs should be set up in district densely populated by EMs, so that EM jobseekers can gain access to the labour department case management and intensive employment support services.
and it is a special situation that requires specialised employment services, and unlike the labour department's passively implemented measures, which have no statistical evidence of success. Thank you. Thank you, Ms Cow. We now have Mrs Zuber-Zubert of the EIM Group, please.
of the EMS, the labour department offering an MBA graduate with a security guard job is a big shameful failure and a loss to the society. The labour department's current measures are not successful, and if they are, please give statistical proof instead of reiterating measures that have been taken.
更新市場情況，Meeting job seekers with suitable vacancies with the employment network in a more efficient manner, addressing their vocational and non-vocational barriers to achieve sustainable employment, connecting job seekers with activities or trainings that will improve their employment opportunities, rendering posi
It's a common belief that those who are Hong Kongians should speak Cantonese, otherwise be responsible for their unemployment. Let me shed light on this. There are multiple valid reasons why a Hongkonger might not know Chinese, and I can testify for one of them, which is the education system not being able to teach Chinese as a second language.
香港居民means香港居民，whether you speak a language or not. And us as Hongkongers, we have equal rights. If equality doesn't get us those rights, then equity should. And this is not a privilege. We strongly propose having a designated task force to open up job opportunities that match the qualifications and abilities.
Hongkongers who do not speak Cantonese are an asset. They are not a burden. They speak different languages. They offer intellect and skills influenced by different ethnic cultures, and definitely are no less than other employees. This is an issue of an ethnic minority population being widely unemployed in a city where there is manpower shortage.
Good afternoon, Chairman and everyone. I'm Miss Zuba. I have higher secondary school education. When I came to Hong Kong, I work as a clerk in a Nepalese company. But since I had a children, then I was not able to go to work because I need to take care of my children. I really want to get a part time job at least, but there is
係。
Good afternoon, everyone.
興趣和 aspirition。
因為長working hours in Hong Kong，和低期望達成職業進步，於課程完成。
In response to the phenomenon, the ERB is recommended to establish a funding for the on-job training incentive, which actually encourage employers to allow employees to go out and work in a reasonable number of hours.
And according to one of our experiences of my friends, there were no jobs to be found after completing an ERB course. She she has done a few two or three courses, but then by the end of the day, she has no job, nothing, and there's no referral offer to any job.
And I think the ERB should review all resources, including application forms of the website, to make sure they are bilingual and equally accessible to all EM community. And the ERB should accept EMs to attend subsidised vocational courses regardless of their employment status and education attainment.
Addressing their vocational and non-vocational barriers to achieve sustainable employment, concerning jobseekers with activities or trainings that will improve their employment opportunities. Thank you. Thank you, Mr. Speaker. We now invite Mr. Chirup Newman, please, of the Hague Group.
Not enough childcare services, and the language barrier is also a big problem. Many employers want to hire people with fluent speaking Cantonese, reading and writing Chinese. That is not fair to us. In Hong Kong, there are many E.M. women who are highly educated, but still it is difficult for them to find jobs.
mostly EM women are level that they do not want to work, are bound by their families and they cannot go out to work. But the reality is that we want to work, contribute our families and really want to support our husband too. But we are not provided enough childcare services opportunities.
To learn Cantonese and join courses to upgrade our skills. Although many of us can at least do a part-time job, even with all problems, we luckily find some job. But we will be paid less than local workers because we do not know Chinese. Although many jobs may not require speaking.
Furthermore, my friends and also I want to take a skill training like Cantonese catering or other professional courses to upgrade ourselves. But the courses time and other requirement do not suit us. Some courses are in the evening or weekends. That makes us impossible to join those.
The following elements would be included in the service: employing case managers, with some of them having EM ethnic backgrounds, to engage with EM jobseekers with intensive follow-up by providing career counselling, exploring their job preferences, commensurate with their qualification experience.
I'm a Pakistani, Hong Kong-born. I'm from a group, a youth concern group about EM employment in Hong Kong over the years. I'm coming across the same problem and the same experience of not being hired in any of the workplaces because of the same issue, which is a language problem. Although I can speak fluent Cantonese and communicate.
with local people with no problem, but the problem is I cannot fully write Chinese and fully read Chinese. So this actually stops most of the employers to hire me. The government is actually responsible to encourage greater flexibility in Chinese language requirement in order to improve EM employment.
我認為一個多樣性如香港，仍缺乏文化及宗教理解。今天，我會花些時間談談鼓勵措施，可惠及我們所有人。第一個我會談的是，我們可以提供補貼給中小企業，以採用積極包容的措施。
which actually benefits both the employer and the employee, and there are jobs such as in IT sector, business sector, in transport industry, hospitality industry where Chinese should not be a major requirement, but then there is. Second, I'd like to talk about is establish a funding for positive measures where encourage employers to create bilingual working.
environment such as translating internal notices and adopt adopting respective adjustments in office setup. Most of the notices in our big companies are all in Chinese version, which actually stops most of the EM job seekers to apply for the job. And studies show that EMs were discouraged to take some ERB courses mainly.
我會想分享我經驗，on ERB courses applying。當我申請ERB course，之後我申請，我get to know that tertiary students or those people who are not working who are working are not apply are not allowed to apply for the course。我諗我只係想提升我的skills，但係我唔被允許。
Another thing is online application version. It's in Chinese, but then the printable forms are in English. I hope the Labour Department will and the ERB will also coordinate with other companies, such as hospitality industry or transport industry, to create more job opportunities for ethnic minorities in Hong Kong. Thank you. Thank you, Mr. Newman.誒，跟住我哋又請吳志遠。
哦。
幾多日先？
謝謝主席。
自那時起，我
自從我香港嚟咗，
Please go ahead if you have, you you're ready.
喺香港，我二十年曆，再大都係嚟緊。
邵爺 chairman，我名Mohammad Gadir，我係香港廿幾年。
Mr. Muhammad Quadir, you wanted to speak ahead first.
先生係E.M.GroupForEmployment嘅。你好，主席，我想問下會唔可以畀二十三號嗰位Claudia先生，因為知道佢有誒急事要走先，後尾畀佢講先，跟住出。冇問題嚇，好唔該。二十三號邊位？二十三號Mr.Claudia。
我們需要有一個特殊的辦公室，就像對於農民而言，需要一個特殊的部門，以便農民獲得他們所需的服務。
我係因為我覺得我哋嘅工作係為咗我哋嘅國家嘅發展，我哋嘅經濟嘅發展，我哋嘅社會嘅發展，我哋嘅民生嘅發展，我哋嘅生活嘅發展，我
我有indaada hoggia tha ke Labour Department ki government ka adara bi nasli apniyo to keliye rozgar ki suliyat achche tarikhe se frame nahi kar raha. I started to realise the lack of the services provided towards the ethnic minorities by the Labour Department since I moved to Hong Kong. मैं और मेरे जैसे दूसरे, दूसरे दो
我這幾年來，政府一直在努力改善我們的服務，讓我們的服務變得更好。每當我們坐在勞工部的辦公室裡，我們都在問政府，如何讓我們的服務變得更好。
就前一陣存在，或某種程度上也沒有帶來任何好處。只有一個勞動部門的就業和就業機會增加。工人們的收入只增加了六個月，而他們的工資只增加了六個月。
一 stop就業支援自己從中解決是不現實的。Every time officials answer things they already have, which are exactly things that didn't help. Nearly nothing much has changed, except having employment service ambassadors who serve last only six months and unable to provide one stop employment.
卡夫爾。
全時。
唔係，唔
我期望我們政府會尊重立法會決議，當議員是由我們選舉。
Full time job，因為，無時刻，教練嘅，最，安全嘅，求。
Advisor to build up the relationship with the employers and provide better opportunity for the ethnic minorities. Thank you very much.
依家唔好忘記，香港嘅議員，或者我哋嘅議員，都係香港嘅市民。我哋嘅議員，我哋
什麼？我們見到今天勞工部正在閉門辦事，不聽取各組織的建議，各委員的動議，以及我們的意見。
工作呢，或我
不少次，議事會的議員團的側面，議事會的議員團不單單是為議事會的議員團的議員
我哋嘅要求係政府應該尊重所有嘅人，包括同性戀者。我哋嘅要求係政府應該尊重所有嘅人，包括同性戀者。我哋嘅要求係政府應該尊重所有嘅人，包括同性戀者。我哋嘅要求係政府應該尊重所有嘅人，包括同性戀者。我哋嘅要求係政府應該尊重所有嘅人，包括同性戀者。我哋嘅要求係政府應該尊重所有嘅人，包括同性戀者。我哋嘅要求係政府應該尊重所有嘅人，包括同性戀者。我哋嘅要求係政府應該尊重所有嘅人，包括同性戀者。我哋嘅要求係政府應該尊重所有嘅人，包括同性戀者。我哋嘅要求係政府應該尊重所有嘅人，包括同性戀者。我哋嘅要求係政府應該尊重所有嘅人，包括同性戀者。我哋嘅要求係政府應該尊重所有嘅人，包括同性戀者。我哋
kisi के राय लिए बगैर तंजीमो इस्हमली के मेम्ब्रान और उनके पास कर्दा मोशन ध्यान नहीं बगैर अपना काम बंद दरवादे के पीछे कर रहे हैं ये किसी तरह भी अच्छा नहीं है
待業的，做咩啊？ 佢哋要揾工，佢哋
來，阿伯，再者，時間加壓做嘅，無人鼻類學科嘅，所以，我覺得
labour department嘅側面，弗範卡達，佢嘅follow or 證據嘅服務嘅應付服務，可以安裝，可以安裝。
考慮嚴肅地設立一個選拔安置分區，為民族少數羣體和指定就業中心（EM）應設立在區內人口密集的EM區，以便EM就業者可獲得勞動部的案件管理及密集就業支援服務。勞動部應聘請專職就業。
啊，equal assets group，please。
我哋 now invite Mr. Sava Iqbal of the
點樣答咧？噉我兩個講法畀大家參詳嚇嚇。第一個講法咧，對我嚟講係道出事實。
拜託咧，大家希望可以真係可以盡快做到一啲改變。噉我哋真係一日都唔等得啦。多謝曬，唔該。唔該，唔該。
個年青人咧，最後咧，除咗地盤保安、洗碗同埋部分嘅外資公司之外咧，發現個市場根本咧就唔侵佢哋玩嘅。
好，Thank you, Mr. Quatelier, and thank you for Madam Interpreter for the interpretation. Now we come back to Mr. the
Good afternoon, my name is Zafar and I have finished my secondary school in Pakistan. I have come to Hong Kong around a year ago. Today I am here to share my job-seeking experience in the Labour Department.
袁先生，好，多謝主席。係大家好，我叫Johnny，我做咗少數族裔青年工作咧，已經三年啦。我亦都係港大社工係嘅碩士學生。咁舊年我成立咗一個關於E.M.嘅青年就業嘅關注組，叫He Group。噉我會就咗經驗咧講一講我前線人員嘅無奈啊。咁喺我日常工作裏邊咧，我需要去培育中中學生。
生嘅自信心啊，引導佢哋發展潛能啊，等等啦。咁但係偏偏嘅現實就好殘酷啊。初中嘅時候咧，佢哋會同你講啊，我想做空姐，我想做誒老師，我想做心理學家嚇。但係去到中學畢業，甚至大專畢業咧，先知道咧，原來咧喺學校學到嘅中文咧啊，攞A都好，公開試攞A都好咧，出到去咧。
程度連小學雞都不如嘅噉，佢會話唔係喎，Sir，我讀account嘅喎，讀曬core嘅喎，入學嗰陣承認我個G.C.S.E嘅喎，出到嚟先至話唔出我玩咁大整蠱嚇嚟到呢一度咧，好啦，噉啊，小弟咧係通常都唔真係唔識答呢班細路噉。我想敢問咧，在座嘅官員，如果畀著你哋咧，你哋會點？
噉我話係啊，真係咁大整故教育制度承認你咧，就唔等於社會要承認你嘅喎。咁多人誒誒幫你咁多咧，仲畀人話你啊正面歧視（positive discrimination）添嚇，唔啱聽唔緊要。仲有第二個version嚇，咁會話唔緊要，我哋揾勞工處啦，佢哋有E.M就業展啦，有業誒就業主任同你分。
識出路啦，仲會幫你聯絡僱主添，係啦。咁下山一萬字噉，希望陣間官員咧可以高抬貴手，唔好再重複一次你哋嘅已有服務啦。係啦，咁以上兩個講法咧，我諗官員咧應該都會揀後者嘅。咁但係結果咧，大家都可能陣間好多嘅誒其他朋友都可以分享下，大家心知肚明。個。
噉你會問啊？我哋作為一個國際城市，其實以誒英文為主嘅工應該都有好多啊。例如機場服務啊、專業嘅個人嘅服務啊，甚至最近講得好多嘅運輸業等等，有冇得搞咧嚇？事實上咧，可能好多前線嘅NGO都可以話到畀你聽，係有得搞嘅，係我哋有做緊嘅服務係prove到係。
有得搞，但係淨係靠NGO現有嘅資源咧揼石仔噉樣做咧，我自己會覺得咧係冇得搞，亦都搞唔曬嚇。所以我哋關注組咧認為，當局咧係真係需要設立一個專責嘅小數族裔就業中心啦嚇。除咗可以提供更加針對性嘅服務咧，亦都要有專專有嘅人。
手去開拓唔同嘅工種啊！嚇，公務員事務局咧都叫做帶頭咧，咁審視咗各個職級嘅合理要求啦。咁夠唔夠就唔喺呢度再講啦。咁會唔會依家就係最好時機咧，將呢一個趨勢咧推廣到去各行各業咧？嚇，咁要達到呢啲目標咧，就絕對唔係印下單張咧，就叫做咗。
係真係，我哋希望要有實質嘅數字去反映到個成效出嚟嚇。呢一點咧，我哋真係好希望咧，誒督導委員會咧可以發揮到佢嘅功效嘅。係最後，我要強調，我哋身邊呢一班年青人咧，全部都係有能力、有知識、有理想嘅香港人。佢哋我哋每拖一日咧，就多一班年青人白白犧牲㗎啦。噉就嚟有DSE啦，噉。
嗯。
Good afternoon, everyone.
財政部應該設立。
這些係僱主，係勞動部門應有。
Good afternoon, everyone. My name is Shumaila. I moved to Hong Kong when I was very small.
job post did not even mention Cantonese requirement, but employers asking for reading and writing Chinese.
通過IES網站，我came across a job at a printing company in Xinwan， which did not require any Chinese.
When I came to Hong Kong, I started looking for job through different means, including Interactive Employment Service of IES of Labour Department.
It is general dissemination of job fairs information catering Chinese job seekers, rather tailor made service for EMs.
當我去面試，僱主説，申請這個職位的應徵者應該會讀寫中文，而拒絕面試。好諷刺啊！
Upemployment opportunities in different sector in order to cater needs of EM job seekers generally. Thank you. Thank you, Mr. Ipoh. We now invite Mrs. Shumaila of the Women Concern Group, please.
and as newly arrived, I thought it is suitable job for me. Job posting mentioned registering Labour Department for job application and I did so both online and in person. Job centre gave me the address of the company to go for the interview.
engage for hiring EMS。 I am very keen in developing a care。 However， there was no other spot provided to me except one job referral on my request and occasionally， I would receive job fair's email， but none of the job is suitable for me as
left helpless from the job centre, I got a casual labour job through help of my father's friend. It has been a year that I have very unstable work. In fact, I am employed even now, but never receive any personnel follow-up from job centre. Currently, with help of Catholic work.
中心，我係Planning on career development and centre is exploring an opportunity for me to be a later mechanic trainee. Had this kind of career counselling was provided to me by labour department, my one year would not have been wasted. Therefore, I strongly demand that.
Disagnet Employment Service Centre of EMS. This centre should include well-trained case managers providing tailor-made career counselling, intensive case follow-up, connecting with vocational and non-vocational training courses and hiring specialist employment adviser for proactively open.
group，please。
S S Reception Reception。
但係， not 足夠 child care 服務。
relevant working experience cannot get a suitable jobs in Hong Kong.
on the other hand， do not acknowledge their skills and talents of E.M.s。
how ironic is it is that on one hand Hong Kong claims having shortage of labour force and
There are many E.M.s who are quite educated, like which with bachelor degrees or above, with.
useless to go to labour department. It is just waste of time. They will not help or follow up your case.
Good afternoon, everyone. My name is Tabasum and I'm and today I'm here to share my husband's experience in seeking employment support from Labour Department.
and want to export labour force there as well as of talent and instrumental to ems potentials.
And the language barrier is also a big problem. Many employers want to hire people with fluent speaking Cantonese, reading and writing Chinese. That is not fair to us.
我 strongly urge the Labour Department to set up designated employment centre for EM so that EM job seeker can gain access to the all these case management and intensive employment support service.
我讀過在 local school，但係我只能講非常 basic Cantonese。幾年之前，我做過廚房助手，有幾次。但係因為我有孩子，我就不可以去工作，因為我需要照顧我的孩子。我真係想找份兼職工作，至少。
eventually they they have to resort to elementary jobs such as such as waiters, construction worker and security guard, etc. Even those jobs are mostly searched by their own network. Our community believe that it's just
There should be career counselling, vocational training, training, job matching and incentive intensive case follow-up service. Reference should be taken from Tinchui One Stop Employment Service for unemployment.
努力將被用於引導僱主在打破障礙方面為EM的就業。我們呼籲政府發起鼓勵和支持的方案，為僱主。謝謝。謝謝，蘇瑪拉。我們現在有Ms. Bibi討論一些我們是超級女性。
skilled worker.
follow-up of any kind.
our family financially.
香港居民，Thank you. Thank you, Mr. de Parcin.
We now invite Miss Arop Sima, also from the Civil Women Group, please. Good afternoon, everyone.
在十二月二零一七，Upon making an appointment to seek employment consultation， I was told that the job
Even though I mentioned that what kind of job I'm looking for and my level of Chinese language proficiency, furthermore, no registration was done nor any other service were provided.
around for half an hour without any proactive assistance from job centre staff. When I find that information displayed is not relevant and not helpful, I approach the reception counter to seek help.
Employer officer told that it will start from tomorrow. However, as we left the job centre and were on the way to home, and we got a call from labour department that it is not starting from tomorrow, and whenever it starts, we will inform you.
接駁員叫EM就業大使，誰填解説表來填寫解説服務的正式。大使然後介紹了約15個工作，但所有都是基本工作，如洗碗、清潔等等，除了一個。
我 husband lost his job in December two thousand and seventeen. Previously, he worked as a general construction worker and experienced unstable employment. So we discussed to seek career guidance from labour department. As my husband wished to develop his career rather than being general worker, because it greatly impacted.
centre on the following recruitment day, as arranged. I visited the job centre along with my husband, and he was arranged to have interview with one employer. After the job interview, we requested to seek help from employment officer as he wished to take training to upgrade his skills to become a.
他 met employment officer and expressed that he wants to take bricklaying training course. The employer officer, after asking basic personal information, mentioned that bricklaying course is not available, but plastering and welding courses are available. My husband agreed to take a plastering course instead.
勞動部門claims to have so-called personalised employment advisory service by experienced employment officer and so-called follow-up service, but I think it is just a joke. As in our experienced employer officer hardly spent ten minutes until today, we have not received any follow-up.
我 strongly recommend that Labour Department should provide designated employment service to EMS, which includes providing career counselling, intensive case follow-up and well-trained employment officers from ethnic minority background to understand better and cater the employment needs of us Hong Kong.
my name is Sima and I was born in Hong Kong. I have bachelor degree in of commerce from Pakistan. I have moved back to Hong Kong after completing my education, and currently I am looking for a job. Earlier this month I visited Labour Department but find it not useful in terms of employment support. I explored.
secondary school。
係，我哋應該講得近啲啲麥克風，請。
and formerly a student of an ESF international.
service that also include labour department, the study findings.
Now we have Mr. Raul Bartica, please, of the EAG group.
except staff telling me to use vacancy machine to find more jobs without any help.
我係一學生， pursuing legal studies at HQ Space。
這是 due to the fact that most job openings available to those raised in Hong Kong.
such as myself require either some proficiency in Cantonese, or a couple of years of related experience.
employment careers for EMs. These centres should include well-trained case managers, providing career
我係目前學生， pursuing legal studies at HQ Space， and formerly students of an ESF international secondary school.
Despite my educational background, I am unable to find a job either in relation to law or even a temporary or part-time job to support my parents.
It was discouraging and disappointing experience. I felt the service of job centre is horrible and nowhere near to what labour department claims, as I found out later on. My experience echoes with findings of recent study on E.M.S. awareness and satisfaction towards selected public.
and my experience show that staff of labour department are friendly and courteous, but as far as finding job is concerned, their service are not useful. Moreover, no employment officer provided me face-to-face personalised employment advisory service, and no information was given on
training courses, including Chinese language courses. Conducting career attitude assessment is just limited to papers of labour department, and I doubt if it has been ever metalised for any EM job seeker. Therefore, I strongly demand that labour department should set up designated
Guidance and consoling, case follow-up service connecting job seekers with trainings that will enhance EM employability, job matching service and specialist employment adviser to proactively open up employment opportunities for EM in diverse sectors. Thank you. Thank you, Miss Sima.
我係想做呢個。
有相當嘅 space for improvement.
另一個改善，那，maybe had。
of more readily accessible talent educated in Hong Kong.
have decided to study abroad with no indication of returning to Hong Kong.
even Chinese-speaking former classmates， with whom I went to secondary school。
是 to ensure that a trained E.M. staff member is employed at every employment centre.
though the labour department staff has accredited itself with actively trying to assist me in finding a job.
this wasted potential is exacerbated by a lot of youth leaving Hong Kong for better opportunities abroad.
Two of which required some proficiency in Chinese, despite my explicit stating that I do not understand Cantonese at all.
earlier this month, I have also visited the Labour Department in Sham Shui Po, in hopes of receiving assistance.
在 my experience of job searching, I have only managed to independently find one job opening within the past year.
who had initially approached me just simply introduced me to an EM staff member, who only managed to aid me in finding three job openings.
一個例子，我建議會係將註冊申請人轉介給經驗或受過訓練的員工，因為中國員工。
這些 job openings are undoubtedly reserved for Chinese speakers and foreign expats, while excluding a large significant portion.
exclusion of non-Chinese speaking persons who spend most of most or all of their lives in Hong Kong can only lead to a brain drain of an increasingly wasted potential.
from whom to.
since I along with
興趣和 aspirations。
我 sure， 幾個其他人， 面對， 問題，， 係， 行， 長， 距離。
to ensure reasonable access to ethnic minorities living around Hong Kong.
要，要有個 face to face access with staff with a staff member， familiar with challenges experienced by the majority of Hong Kongians。
Rendering post recruitment posts to foster effective labour-employer communication on jobs experience. Thank you very much, gentlemen. Thank you, Mr. Sarah.跟住我哋請誒社會民主連線吳文遠先生。唔該曬。
Thank you for your time. Thank you, Mr. Balthazar. We now have Mrs. Abis Syra, please. Thank you, Chairman. My name is Syra, and I have master degree, and I also have done bachelor in education. Originally, I am professionally teacher. I was born in Hong Kong, but brought up and studied back in Pakistan. I have been working in.
This NGO from last almost 11 years. In my experience working in Yaocheng District, it is very easy to build up network among ethnic minority community if you know their language. This is a good step that Labour Department hired EM ambassadors and employment assistants. It is good for young generation training, but
Not good or beneficial for service user at all. But we notice that it seems to be not useful to hire someone with just secondary level education. And also youngsters, maybe they are not mature enough to have understanding of EM employment and its difficulties. There should be employment officers and employment assistance.
with ethnic minority background, with at least university degree and experience enough to tackle the employment problem of ethnic minorities. Even in NGOs who are serving EMs, they hire people with university degrees. Then why not labour department? We do have many highly educated EMs, and it will be.
會利用他們的才能以這種方式，而且會對服務使用者非常有益。在我們的NGO，最近我們開始了就業服務。我們有諮詢和個案跟進服務。即使我們沒有足夠的人力，但我們盡力提供指定的就業服務，根據個別。
視覺 needs of job seekers. We urge labour department to set up designated employment centres for ethnic minorities in district mostly populated by ethnic minorities, so that EM job seekers can gain access to the LDS case management and intensive employment support services. There should be case.
與一些有族裔少數背景的案管員，與EM職業尋求者互動，進行密集的追蹤。這些案管員應提供以下支援服務：他們應提供職業諮詢，探索職業尋求者的偏好，並與其資格和經驗相匹配。
They should be provided information on local work culture and updated market situations. There should be job matching service with suitable vacancies within employer network in a more efficient manner. And there should there should be some vocational and non vocational training courses that can after.
得到那種訓練，他們應該有可持續的就業。他們應該也提供一些連接，之間就業尋求者和僱主，並嘗試改善就業機會給族裔少數羣體。然後，最後但並非最不重要的，就是應該有。
要嘅香港人之外咧。
叫誒，甚至乎係啲僱主咧，都係因為佢哋啲誒語言問題啊，或者誒中文要求啊，誒，但係其實我哋要睇遠啲嘅。
到我friends從The EM communities，excuse me for conducting my speech in Chinese。我just want to have more Hong Kong people understand your daily lives and your difficulties。嗱，各位其實少數族裔咧喺香港面對嘅問題都唔少嘅。我想強調一點咧，就係少數族裔。
嘅都係香港人啊！我哋政府咧都係要有責任去幫助佢哋，甚至乎要投放更加多資源幫助佢哋嘅啊。因為佢哋每日面對嘅咧，除咗係呢個啊語言嘅障礙嘅問題之外咧啊，亦都有好多啊工作環境不同嘅啊隱性歧視啊。
嘅行為噉啊，令到誒好多誒本身係有志去貢獻社會嘅少數罪嘅人士咧，就面臨一啲非常之不必要嘅困難。誒嗱，當然啦，啱啱有好多朋友咧，佢哋都話誒，因為喺勞工署嗰度咧，就誒面對即係一啲困難噉，最主要。
啱啱我哋見到，其實好多小數族裔嘅佢哋係有知識嘅，誒有啲係高學歷嘅，啊，亦都係語言咧，特別係佢哋誒英文程度咧，係遠遠高過我覺得係遠遠高過誒普通嘅一個華裔香港人嘅，甚至乎有啲立法會議員添。咁所以點解？
佢哋都會面對噉嘅障礙咧，就係因為政府係當佢哋就係少數啊嘛。誒，唔需要理佢哋啊嘛。誒，唔理少數族裔嘅，又唔會影響到你嘅選舉嘅，亦唔會影響到你施政嘅。咁所以咪將啲資源係求其投放咗，佢就算數啊。嗱，當然啦，誒。
勞工署就會話：其實我哋都做咗嘢嘅，噉我哋都請咗兩條友就做呢個誒就業助理，去幫助呢少數族裔。大佬都兩個人，即係新增啊！我講緊新增嘅誒呢啲誒呢啲職位啊。其實我哋認為誒勞工署應該放眼遠啲，誒投放更加多資源與。
如果你可以用話五億十億嚟支援一啲中小企，去幫佢哋做推廣，去海外推廣啊，推廣一帶一路啊，做啲咁誒賭錢落海嘅嘢，點解唔將五億十億嘅調翻轉頭擺翻喺香港人屬於香港嘅少數族裔身上咧？誒，做一個誒專責。
部門係解決少數族裔嘅就業問題誒問題啊，亦都唔係淨係話幫佢哋去誒揾工啊，更加需要嘅咧就係要教育香港嘅僱主啊，令到佢哋要踢開咗嗰種隱性歧視嗰種誒嗰個嗰嗰嗰種枷鎖，唔好諗住係話咧誒，因為呢個。
成成個社會啊，對呢個小數族裔嘅標籤咧，而令到佢哋卻步啊。而當然啦，最根本性嘅就係政府應該要誒從根源入手，由香港細蚊仔、小數族裔細蚊仔嘅誒嘅嘅時候咧，就應該改革個制度，投投放更加多資源，令到有。
佢哋咁多人係唔識中文啊，亦都即係你咁多嘅工作，其實誒，甚至乎淨係用中文寫嘅時候，佢哋肯定係需要傳譯㗎。咁點解會得二十次咧？係咪呢一個傳譯嘅服務，又或者係即係職員去介紹畀佢哋嘅時候嘅嗰一個成效太低咧？
要做好嘅本分。另外一樣嘢咧，就係政府點樣去帶頭做起咧？唔係淨係靠印單張鼓勵，自己本身究竟係請咗幾多小數族裔嘅工作咧？我哋睇到大家都提議勞工處要有就業嘅支援主任，但係我睇到嘅唔單止係勞工處。
特定嘅課程去配合翻誒，畀啲小數族裔細蚊仔，同埋能夠令到佢哋銜接到，無論中學去到大學，去到就業社會。如果唔係咧，個我哋呢個問題，或者小數族裔就就業問題咧，只會沒完沒了。而最後我就係講多一句，除咗係我哋本身係香港住嘅小數族裔。
勞工處政府係應該檢視同埋批准誒，等待緊審批嘅難民咧，都有機會喺香港就業。嗱，如果呢啲嘢你都唔做嘅話咧，你唔好同我講，特別係工聯會嗰啲唔好同我講話咧。誒，要引入外地勞工，因為香港你好缺乏勞工。我哋本身香港就係。
有好多有能力有skill嘅員工，誒嘅嘅嘅香港人，少數族裔，係只係你哋係漠視佢哋啫。唔該，唔該，吳生跟住係請社民聯嘅周樂行先生，唔該，係誒勞資糾紛咧，需要調停服務，又或者係勞工需要查詢僱用條例嘅時候咧，佢哋要。
去揾勞資關係科嘅噉，但係個嗰啲嘅分處咧個辦公時間就真係只係辦公時間啦。星期一至星期五噉樣咁誒，其實無論本地定還是係誒少數族裔又好華裔又好，其實都難求助。只有星期日先至放假嘅誒外籍家務工咧就。
更加係有冤無路訴嘅噉。另外一方面咧，誒職業介紹嘅話咧，勞工處嘅互動就業服務網站，我唔知誒而家勞工處啊噉樣嘅代表咧有冇上過呢個網站啊？jobstock.gov.hk啊嚇噉啊誒，勞工處嘅文件又好，政府嘅網頁又好，成日都。
講呢個網站嘅，但係上到去嘅時候咧，我就好畀心機揾㗎啦。但係我就始終都揾唔到咧其他語言究竟喺邊度嘅。噉我後屘咧，我就發現到，但係我點樣發現咧？我就喺統計處嘅報告咧，先至發現到有一個網站咧，就叫做jobs.gov.hk後邊咧。
就要加翻e.m.原來噉，你個連結喺邊度先得嘅，大佬。即係希望咧，政府其實都唔知勞工署嘅啦，所有政府部門啲網站都係噉嘅，啲服務唔知拎咗去邊度嘅。咁嚟誒網站都搞成噉嘅話咧，實體支援服務就梗係更加差啦。即係睇翻二零一七年勞工署。
就曾經向誒即係二千八百四十四個少數族裔嘅求職人士就介紹傳譯服務，咁但係咧就只有二十次咧就有安排到嘅。噉我諗誒可能署方就梗係會話，哦嗰啲人自己話唔需要啦。但係我諗即係用一個常理去諗，少數族裔喺喺香港。
咁另外一方面咧，就誒根據香港少數族裔人士嘅貧窮情況呢一個報告咧，其實南亞裔人士投身勞動市場嘅比例咧，比起即係平均嘅香港人更加高。咁但係南亞裔嘅家庭咧，如果有細路仔嘅話咧，佢哋嘅貧窮率咧就比全香港
平均咧係高出一倍，咁所以呢個問題咧就完全係見到個社會上邊一個種族歧視好嚴重，咁但係零九年生效嘅種族歧視條例咧又唔cover即係政府嘅職能同埋職權嘅，跟住到到一零年咧嗰個種族平等行政指引咧理論上就係保。
保留啦噉，但係堂堂政府出份指引咧，又冇法定效力，啲部門參與啊，就係所謂嘅自願性質咁變咗，即係誒一啲無論社處又好定話成日勞工處又好，佢哋係冇跟足個指引，又或者係即係達唔到個指引嘅標準嘅話咧，完全係無從問責嘅，又或者係有一啲。
嘅政府部門，即係政誒警察啊、海關啊噉樣咧，就帶頭係誒誒規定嗰一個申請人咧嘅中英文能力係要達標嘅。噉啊，率先就削減少數族嘅就業嘅機會。咁但係由教育開始，佢哋就已經冇一啲合適嘅教育，變咗佢哋好多人。
政策同埋喺唔同嘅部門都應該要設立一啲。
誒青少年噉樣，噉樣其實冇意思。
原因咧，往往就係因為語言嘅隔膜，所以咧就令到佢哋備受剝削啦。即使咧係公司話咧係會即係啊。
咁所以政府咧喺呢一度咧應該要有一個全面一站式嘅服務，係喺唔同嘅跨度誒跨越唔同嘅政策層面去幫呢啲少數族裔。
做翻好啲，但係咧仍然咧係反口嘅。咁第二樣嘢就係大家還記得上年三月咧，港珠澳大橋嘅工業意外入邊咧，係有三個。
人都講過啦，我嚟過幾次少數族嘅公聽會嘅，即係好多人佢讀完大學，但係個中文能力都咁低嘅時候，噉你講咩就業啫？佢點有可能有一個向上流動嘅機會啫？咁時間關係，我講到最後一句啦，就係每次講到種族平等嘅時候咧，真係唔該外用喺香港工作咁多年，佢絕對係我。
我哋家庭嘅一份子嚟嘅，即係外傭必須要有居港權。如果今次係講呢啲噉嘅就業服務嘅時候咧，如果外傭有居港權，咁勞工署就應該給範圍佢哋。唔該，唔該，周生。跟住我請社區前進胡瑞山女士。唔該誒，唔該，主席。咁頭先好多團體提過關於一啲就業就業支援服務嘅問題咧，我哋都非。
非常之同意，亦都喺度唔重複啦。我喺呢一度今日想講下嘅咧，係政府嘅責任，支援少數族裔嘅就業，唔係淨係勞工處嘅責任，係社整個政府整體嘅責任嚟。好似而家好多少數族裔嘅婦女，尤其是尼泊爾嘅婦女，係做緊好多政府外判嘅清潔工，但係佢同本地嘅華裔婦女好唔同嘅咧，就係。
佢要做兩份嘅，一朝頭早做灣仔，跟住誒夜更咧做，再做六個鐘就走去西環嗰度。點解啊？因為咧啲少數族裔婦女咧，佢哋家庭嘅男性成員其實個人工都好低啦，亦都係就業不穩。於是佢哋咧就搏晒去做嘢。噉啊，點解會導致啲？
到呢個情況啫，政府自己製造出嚟嘅嗰啲外判工作，啲人工都低到可恥嘅。咁結果呢啲噉樣嘅喺外判政府嘅外判工作裏邊做緊嘅少數族裔婦女咧，就要打兩份呢啲噉嘅外判工咧，先至可以維生。咁點解政府淨係話要鼓勵其他僱主，淨係睇到人？
地點解你唔倒翻轉頭望一望你自己？你製造緊一啲點樣嘅就業機會畀少數族裔先？如果你都係製造呢一啲咁可恥、咁不合理嘅就業機會嘅話，你憑咩叫嗰啲私人機構去提供一個合理嘅待遇咧？你自己都唔能夠以身作則，所以政府根本就自己應該。
政府最叻宣傳嘅係乜嘢咧？我哋呈教處同警處請咗好多少數族裔係啊。我拉你嘅時候，罰你嘅時候咧，就識得揾少數族裔咧嚟做啦。社處咧、教育處咧、房處咧、醫管局咧，幫少數族裔嗰啲又唔見你請少數族裔嚟做哇？噉你咪好著數。
你咪好，即係咪揾笨嘅呢啲，即係根本就喺度標籤緊少數族裔，就係咩幫緊少數族裔，所以整體嚟講，政府應該係要有一個中係一個中央嘅喺政策層面嘅一個促進種族共融嘅一個工作嘅一個特別嘅小組，然後係喺唔同嘅政府部門檢視佢哋嘅政。
係負責專責負責種族共融嘅一啲職員，呢啲係公務員嚟嘅，係穩定優質嘅就業，同埋喺每一個政策層面同埋喺具體服務裏邊去諗點樣去幫少數族裔嚇，唔係淨係落去嚇喺喺揾啲少數族裔嚟咧喺街度截查啲少數族裔嘅嘅。
係唔該，胡小姐、胡女士，跟住又請工黨嘅郭永健先生。大家好。咁咧喺香港咧，好多人就話，即係條街上面好多南亞裔啊，或者好多少數族裔咧，就話佢哋係假難民或者標籤咧，所有即係南亞裔嘅人士都係即係有犯罪嘅傾向。但係好多嘅工作係好。
危險嘅，包括地盤嘅工作啦，包括係外賣車手嘅工作。其實咧，往往都係由最基層嘅少數族裔人士去擔當。噉，試問嗰一啲批評話少數族裔有犯罪傾向嘅人，睇唔睇到佢哋呢啲嘅付出咧？睇唔睇到佢哋其實係為香港嘅社會係。
奉獻緊佢哋嘅勞動力，而佢哋往往咧係喺最危險嘅工作環境工作咧。咁大家睇翻就係一月初咁有餐飲速遞公司Deliver就有個罷工，咁入邊咧其實好多車手都係一啲少數族裔嚟嘅，有巴基斯坦啦、印度啦，當然亦有香港人。咁但係佢哋嘅勞工權。
唔會畀佢哋。
噉佢。
嘅職業收入中位數只係九千二百蚊，比起。
我必須要為佢哋提供足夠嘅支援，喺就業方面幫佢哋融入社會，改善佢哋嘅生活嘅。
呢一樣嘢係少數族裔進入就業市場嘅時候咧，令到佢哋嘅職業選擇往往都非常之少。
危險時薪較低、工時亦都比較長嘅工作啦。其實呢個亦都係解釋到點解佢哋嘅收入中位數係咁低嘅原因。
其實好多時候，少數族裔喺就業方面最困難嘅地方，就因為佢哋廣東話唔叻啦，或者佢哋寫唔到中文字啦。其實呢一個，
喺求職或者就業以至生活所遇到困難嘅問題啦，其實呢樣嘢政府係必須要盡快全面檢討現時為少數族裔學生定立嘅中國語文課程。
咁其實，即使有一大部分嘅少數族裔其實曾經接受過高等教育啦，亦都講到流利嘅廣東話嘅，但係因為佢哋嘅中文寫作能力欠佳，或者唔識睇中文字咧，令到佢哋唔獲聘用嘅。
嘅即係工人係死亡兩死三傷嘅工業意外係兩名工人咧就係少數族裔啦。咁其實咧就話畀大家聽，往往咧我哋啲少數族裔咧，佢哋係工作嘅環境嘅危險咧，係受到勞工處啦，受到咧係僱員嗰個補償嗰度咧係被受忽略。
嘅有個研究咧，就指出香港少數族裔嘅工傷比率咧，係高過本地嘅工人，係咧比起本地工人高出三成有多嘅。咁咧，往往就係好多即係機器嘅指示咧係冇中文啦，佢哋嘅即係上司係唔識同佢哋用英文溝通，但係咧就要佢哋咧去即係操作。
一啲好危險嘅工具，同埋咧就要即刻去做嘢啦。咁呢啲咧都係造成我哋見到噉嘅情況。咁而睇翻在職貧窮嘅問題咧，喺少數族裔嗰度咧都係非常之常見。大家睇翻一六年嘅貧窮報告，而家咧成個少數族裔嘅貧窮率咧係十九點四個。
percent係不減反增嘅。大家睇翻二零一一年咧，佢哋嗰個比率咧係只不過十五點八個percent啫。即使咧有政策介入之後咧，都係只不過跌咗一點八個percent咧。咁説明咗咩咧？在政府嘅服務咧係幫唔到佢哋，無論咧係一啲現金津貼嘅援助。
長生津又好，或者係在職嘅即係家庭津貼又好咧，其實佢哋申領嘅人咧都係偏低嘅。咁呢個咧就係話畀大家聽，政府自己嘅服務都做唔好。其實咧呢啲全部都有研究係話畀大家知嘅。譬如有個係少數族裔人士對主要公共服務嘅認知和滿意程度研究入邊咧，都係講出咧。
好多即係受訪嘅少數族裔都係話畀大家聽咧。其實勞工署啊，或者咧係即係再培訓局咧啲服務係幫唔到佢哋係廢嘅。包括咧即係大家睇到啦，有成億過往咧上年有一千個係使用就業服務嘅，但係獲聘嘅個人只有七十五宗，成功率係七點五個。
percent咁單憑呢個數字咧就可見一斑。咁希望咧，政府係要深切去檢討做好咧有關就業服務嘅配套，畀少數族裔人士咧可以係改善貧窮問題。唔該，國生。跟住請公民黨伍曉雯小姐。唔該。誒，多謝主席。其實誒頭先亦都有議會姐提到嘅就係其實少數族。
裔嘅勞動人口參與咧，其實比香港人更加高啦。但係同時間，佢哋有小朋，即係誒少數族裔有小朋友嘅家庭咧嘅貧窮率係比香港嘅家庭為高啦。其實睇翻誒二零一六年政府發布嗰個香港少數族裔人士貧窮報告入邊，其實都其實都講到，其實少數族裔主要嘅
香港嘅工作人口嘅入息中位數一萬五千蚊，其實有非常之大嘅距離啦。其實呢日都見到，其實就算香港有經濟增長，如何強勁，都佢哋係冇辦法分享到呢個經濟嘅成果。其實港民黨認為，即使既既然大部分嘅少數族裔都係香港嘅常住居民啦，其實政府。
其實同時間啦，其實由於社會普遍對少數族裔存在非常之多嘅誤解啦，其實例如就係佢哋講到廣東話，雖然佢哋講到廣東話，但係其實僱主會認即係睇到個誒佢哋send嚟嘅履歷嘅時候，會認為佢哋係因為少數族裔以致講唔到廣東話，所以連見工嘅機會都。
其實現時係有三十三點五個percent嘅少數族裔係曾經接受過專上教育，咁唔少甚至擁有專業資格。但係其實由於佢哋喺屋即係喺佢哋家鄉考獲嘅專業資格咧，喺香港不被承認，咁所以以致佢哋嚟到香港嘅時候，好多時候都被迫從事一啲誒低技術危。
會 help government.
integration among ethnic minority population.
我們相信，設立社區 officer 基金。
to facilitate contract-based as well as short-term employment.
many ethnic minority populations share similar stories with me, and today I'm speaking on behalf of all of them.
After completing six months of acquiring the skills and training from the youth training programme for ethnic minority, E.M. population find it difficult.
to bring one step closer to promote social integration, mutual trust as well as long term relationship with ethnic minority population. Thank you.
它開始影響我 mentaly。我開始 losing confidence in myself，questioning my capabilities and losing the motivation to work。 at the end，我 had to switch towards a different career path to start afresh。
many well-qualified, skilful and experienced EM persons face different challenges and barriers to get a job when they move to Hong Kong. Not only persons who have moved to Hong Kong, but also people living in Hong Kong face similar situation.
however, even after clearing several rounds of interviews, I still heard back the same reply of requiring someone knowing the language. This did not happen once, but many times. Not getting an opportunity to even prove myself at first place was disturbing.
咁其實作為香港嘅一份子啦，公民黨認為生活喺香港嘅少數族類少數族裔應該同其他居民一樣擁有同等嘅權利，亦都有必要融入本地嘅生活。所以提升少數族裔嘅中文水平，令到佢哋唔會因為語言嘅問題而產生障礙，呢個先係根本地去解決少數族裔。
幫幫佢哋慢慢慢慢提升佢哋中文嘅讀寫能力，因為其實現時喺香港誒少數族裔喺學校入邊喺得唔到一個誒足夠嘅支援去學中文，因為佢哋始終係第二個語言。噉我覺得呢樣嘢政府係必須要正視嘅。多謝多謝。唔該，吳小姐。誒，We now invite Miss
Wetta Anand, please. Good evening, everyone. I moved to Hong Kong from India four years ago. I'm happy to say that despite many apprehensions about moving to a new city, it was easy to settle in, thanks to all the great people and facilities in one of the most convenient city. However, challenges begin when I started looking for the job.
even with qualifications as healthcare professional with past working experience, I faced difficulty in getting employment. Given the language constraints, that too written as well as oral, I was not eligible for most of the opportunities. Luckily, for some opportunities, I successfully managed to get interview.
to find the employment opportunities. That is why we are proposing the community officer fund, which will help EM population to get an opportunity to enhance their skills and gain practical working experience. Setting up of this fund will help the public service departments.
using this one to support remuneration of the employed EM. This pilot model is already being successfully followed by labour department, where they have employed EM population as employment ambassadors. We are thankful for government to earmark five hundred million dollars in the recent budget to promote social
thank you, Miss Lennon。跟住我哋請醫護行者嘅劉海玲小姐，唔該。唔該，主席。醫護行者今日就即係整合一啲我哋過往幾年同小數聚做健康嘅一啲意見啦，同埋啱啱上一位講者有提到，其實啱啱誒財政預算案有講到政府用咗五億去即係鼓勵小數聚融入社會嘅，咁所以就住誒呢五。
五億啦，同埋近排發放好多講者都提到兩份報告，一份報告係講跟少數族裔貧窮，特別係巴基斯坦裔嚴重嘅問題啦。另一份就係少數族裔尋求公營服務時遇到嘅困難咧。其實我哋覺得呢五億都係一個良機嚟嘅。噉我哋有四個建議，希望就聽下局方有啲乜嘢回應嘅。第一個係頭先上位講者講。
Good evening, everyone.
得啦，唔該，謝謝。唔該，樓謝謝。We now invite Mrs. Nazim Akter, please.
資助嘅基金，例如係可以參考誒，對於。
courses at ERB to increase her chance of employment, but it is also not helpful. She wanted to go to labour department to seek help.
到一個community officer份，其實我哋一個想像咧，就係因為勞工處其實好好。其實有一個例子就係之前請咗隻employment assistant啦，亦都有大使。其實喺唔同嘅政府部門或者局入邊，其實係一個好好嘅即係示範啦。其實亦都睇到政府係可以領導或者即係比起私營市場睇到係可以。
即係聘用多一啲嘅小數聚嘅噉，我哋期望呢一個即係分係鼓勵，無論係私營啦，甚至乎公營都可以有一啲即係更多元化嘅就業嘅機會。噉就喺呢五億入邊咧，就預留一啲撥款咧，係能夠鼓勵公營或者即係私營嘅僱主係能夠聘請可能一啲短期合約嘅小數聚，等佢哋有多一啲就業嘅機會。
會，亦都同時另一方面，如果呢啲僱主開始嘗試聘用少數族裔，可能就睇到佢哋嗰個價值，甚至乎令到個工作環境咧更加對於少數族裔友善嘅。咁呢個就等到去第二個嘅誒意見啦。噉就係關於點樣令到一啲僱主或者就業嘅環境有更加少數族裔友善咧？因為頭先好多港姐分享。
自己嘅經歷嘅時候，其實睇到嗰個源頭咧，誒唔係話即係局方唔努力去幫佢哋揾工作，而係好多時真係私營市場僱主咧係未必能夠切合少數族裔嘅需要。噉我哋都聽到有唔少少數族裔講啊，就算佢真係揾到一份工咧，其實佢哋做得唔長嘅原因係佢真係開始做嘢嘅。
時候發現，可能工作環境好多嘢係未必佢睇得明啦。又或者其實同事之間咧唔係好明白，可能唔同即係族裔或者誒一啲誒種族上即係religion上嘅需要嘅。咁所以我哋就希望，如果五億入邊咧有噉樣嘅一個即係多元化就業嘅即係基金或者資助咧，係能夠可以誒。
畀僱主私人嘅僱主去申請，去令到佢哋嘅工作環境更加友善嘅，例如譬如我哋作為一個細嘅N G O咧，誒一個困難，有時就係發覺其實我哋要翻譯入中文同英文，其實個翻譯費用係昂貴，所以對於私人企業嚟講，可能誒嗰個會係一個barrier咯。咁假如政府可能有啲資助嘅，係能夠畀呢啲。
僱主去申請去令到佢哋工作環境更加少數族優先，其實我相信會更多僱主係願意去即係聘請少數族嘅同事嘅。咁最後因為時間關係，咁兩個好快嘅建議，一個咧就係關於誒頭先其實有講者提到關於社企嘅好多時，我哋巴基斯坦因為佢哋貧窮率特別高啦，但係婦女可能未必能夠出去就業。咁其實如果有一啲誒。
誒勞工處喺聘請誒一啲殘疾人士上面咧，其實有個基金咧，係畀佢哋去做社企嘅。咁如果小數聚聚，其實類似有個基金係鼓勵Angie都好或者私人企業係能夠啲社企製造就業機會畀小數聚聚咧，噉係好理想啦。咁最後一個咧係關於誒工傷嘅問題，因為事實上我哋做即係醫療。
就睇到其實特別係少數族巴基斯坦裔嘅嘅男士咧，如果佢可能係從事一啲高危嘅工作，例如係即係地盤工嘅，其實佢一傷咗咧，就好容易令個成個家庭都跌落貧窮線。咁所以好希望喺嗰個工傷度同埋我哋前線都聽到好多男士，特別係尼泊爾男士咧，佢哋話誒，其實佢哋想得到多一啲工。
商或者職業健康嘅資訊嘅，但係無奈地甚至乎喺地盤上一啲翻譯咗嘅健康嘅資訊咧，佢哋話都係譯錯咗嘅。咁所以都想即係帶出就係其實誒少數最多係想係即係做嘢上係健康啲，但係可能就爭緊嗰個誒合適度，又或者佢哋個資訊未必能夠真係誒切合佢。
Good evening, everyone. My name is Nisim Akhtar and I am here today to talk about employment difficulties that my daughters faced in Hong Kong. I have two daughters. They finished their secondary school in Pakistan and moved to Hong Kong seven years ago. But they find it very difficult to get
幾時得㗎？
但The elder daughter told her。
as as the most of our Chinese customers will be scared and therefore will not come to the hotel.
Visit Labour Department. My daughter mentioned that job vacancies welcoming application from EMs in Labour Department.
website，website are mostly elementary jobs like cleaning, dishwashing and so on. When my daughters called some employers,
practice. It is the responsibility of labour departments to engage with employers to discuss with them about the talent and potential.
That going to labour department it not helpful in getting a suitable job because of her unfruitful experience in visiting labour department. So she mentioned that it waste of time.
suitable jobs. So my elder daughter found a job with help of an NGO, which is not an EM sports service centre. My younger daughter is actively looking for a job for last four months and she has attended different kind of
They speak in Cantonese only and hang up the calls. So she also went to some of EM support service centres, but they have not provide much help except taking name and contact number and told that we.
會get back。Recently, my daughters went for the interview of the receptionist position in a hotel. The HR officer mentioned that we want to offer you this job, but you need to take off your hijab.
所以如果你 wish to work， 那你就要 remove 你的 hijab。 我的女兒很失望和傷心， 由於這個回應， 而拒絕了這個 offer， 因為它會干擾我們的宗教。
That EMs can bring to their businesses special young educated EMs. Neither labour department nor employers have much understanding on our cultural and religious practice. Labour department should hire full time.
University graduate employment officers from EM background to provide in-depth employment consultation, career guiders and follow up the EM job seeker until they get job successfully. Thank you.
係地盤保安、運輸誒，對於佢哋嘅向上流動嘅機會係非常之少嘅。咁誒。
those job were not stable, and it was quite difficult to manage the expenses of the five family members.
我覺得喺香港，我係Chinese、English兩字都唔夠，想揾工都好難。我嚟到呢度，我試過好多工，都唔得。
We now have Mr. Amex Khan of the E.M. Employment Group. Through, Madam Interpreter, please.
界嚟講，都係一個示範嘅作用，亦都令到少數族裔嘅朋友可以覺得呢度係一個落地生根嘅地方。咁最後就希望誒今次與會之後，希望政府保有一個非常之積極嘅態度去解決呢個問題。唔該，曾生。
Hello, my name is Amrith Khan. I came to Hong Kong around three and half years before. I found that it was almost impossible to find any job in Hong Kong if you do not know English or Chinese. I was in so much difficulty.
我有沒有資格申請？
誒，跟住又請香港天主教勞工事務委員會曾家俊先生，唔該。係唔該。誒，今日咧雖然評議會冇與會啦，咁但係佢都提咗一份意見書入嚟咧。咁入面其實睇一啲少數族裔嘅就業問題咧，我哋衷心都發覺其實好有共鳴、好有同感嘅。但係我睇完之後就發覺，誒，其中一個好重要嘅重點。
點係一路？我哋覺得政府做得唔夠嘅就係佢哋有誒缺乏一種積極嘅態度去解決一個誒E.M.嘅誒勞工問題嘅咁誒。例如我講翻一個喺服務層面上面咧，我哋會主動去聯絡一啲僱主咧，去建議佢哋聘請翻少數族裔嘅朋友嘅咁誒。發現咧，其實唔少僱主咧有興趣。
佢想試下身，誒試下請佢哋嘅，但係咧唔知從何入手嘅，亦都好缺乏支援嘅。佢哋想揾人，除咗能力之外，佢哋另一個考慮就係誒嗰位少數族裔嘅背景啦，可唔可靠啦？呢樣嘢誒，佢哋係好好緊張嘅。噉佢哋唔請一部分係除咗能力嘅問題之外，另一部分佢哋擔心自。
自己冇能力喺工作環境上面配合到呢班少數族裔嘅朋友，誒驚同佢哋難溝通啦，誒文化差異好大啦，宗教誒都大家個認識都好少啦，誒令到大家都好睏難。咁誒有啲咧，甚至會將佢哋同一啲誒號型申請者誒撈亂啦，驚請咗佢哋之後咧。
咧會等於請咗黑工啦，咁誒或者以為所有嘅小業族裔都係新移民、新來港嘅朋友，咁誒我哋認為咧，僱主咧同埋求職者中間咧嗰個誒紅溝係好大嘅，咁作為一個服務機構，我哋咧會扮演中間嘅橋樑，促進佢哋誒有接觸啦、有溝通啦，會話畀佢聽呢個小業族裔嘅。
朋友，佢有咩優點，有咩好處？誒，你請佢之後可以幫你解決啲咩問題？我哋會持續介紹啲工作畀啲求職者，會有一個個案跟進，亦都會向翻啲僱主去挑選一啲合適嘅誒求職者，為咗解決呢樣嘢，我哋試過同僱主講誒伊斯蘭教徒佢哋每日嘅祈禱安排可以點做啦，佢可以。
以誒點樣可以更加安全地佩戴頭巾啦？誒，令到佢哋喺工作間上面可以更加安全、更加舒服。僱主對於呢樣嘢係非常之認同，亦都非常之誒欣賞嘅。噉我覺得喺呢度誒，勞工處應該要考慮設立呢個少數族裔嘅就業中心，支援翻僱主去聘請啲少數族裔，例如幫佢哋將佢哋工作有。
關嘅文件咧，誒翻譯翻去少數族裔嘅語言，支持翻少數族裔嘅朋友咧，誒建立翻一個文化誒共融嘅環境啦，誒或者開一啲唔同嘅計劃，去培訓佢哋擔任一啲高技術嘅工種，因為我哋見到好多少數族裔其實都係從事一啲基層嘅勞動工作，誒做嚟做去都。
持續跟進佢哋嘅時候，改變僱主對佢哋一種誒既定嘅既定嘅諗法，就係啊，佢哋都係基層嚟嘅。誒，佢哋都唔會長做我哋嘅工作嘅，佢哋當然要甩底。誒，呢呢個部分呢啲呢啲情況係可以逐步逐步咁改善，慢慢佢哋對於佢哋有信心嘅時候咧，會有更多嘅僱主咧願意去請少數族裔嘅。咁另外一個部，
部分咧就係誒今年財政預算案咧留咗五億，或支持支持呢個小數族裔啦。但係我哋認為政府作為香港最大嘅僱主，聘用十七萬嘅人啦。咁但係誒，我哋發現佢哋聘請小數族裔嘅部分咧，其實好少嘅啫。但係如果你開始聘請小數族裔喺唔同嘅部門揾佢哋翻嚟幫手嘅時候，對於商
要被addressed。
my friend believes that it's just waste of time to go to the labor department. They will never help to find jobs.
我比你揾工度，我唔係好叻。
然後，這中心在減薪申請補貼方面幫我，他們告訴我勞動部也是一個幫我找工作的部門。
勞工一族的，特別是年輕人，他們的收入，
and on the other hand, organising employers' educational and promotional activities to enhance the local employers' understanding of the working abilities of EM job seekers and to cultivate a positive attitude towards EM job seekers. Thank you very much. Thank you, Mr. Karlen. Thank you, Madam Interpreter, for interpretation.
我嘅鄉村嘅幾位朋友喺度，我同佢哋聯繫，佢哋幫我揾幾份臨時工。我嘅家鄉嘅幾位朋友喺度，我同佢哋聯繫，佢哋幫我揾幾份臨時工。
我自從從來都做過很多種工作，我從來都做過很多種工作，我從來都做過很多種工作。
我工作做建築工人和保安，自那時起薪金並不高，很低，而且很難生存。我比中國本地工人低薪，因為我不會中文，所以也無法為自己的權利而抗爭。
我唔知有咩公或政府資源可以幫我揾到好工，或申請低收入補貼。冇人從來冇介紹我，或告知我，有個部門係叫勞動部，可以幫我揾工。我好幸運，我朋友介紹我去一個就業中心，可以幫我揾工。
by by chance, one of my friend introduced me the Catholic Working Centre, and then this NGO helped me to apply for the low income subsidies and introduced me that the Labour Department is one responsible to help in finding the jobs。我朋友講嘅係，去 Labour Department 去只係揾工，做嘢，做嘢係。
這中心，或我幾友誼，我知馬，馬路冇話，勞動部部門嘅人，有幾少少，幾多幾
那比較多鬧劇和爭議，例如語言問題、文化差異、一些人對動物的不尊重，以及主人對動物的虐待。這些問題需要得到解決。
謝謝。
In that case, we have it copied and sent out to members then.
好誒，時間關係咧，就誒，我哋馬上處理咗誒。
或者噉，我先處理咗毛漢靜議員嗰個誒動議先啦。不過提一提咧，就我唔想聲張下毛漢靜議員嘅意見，因為你嗰個動議咧雖然係英文啦，但係你嗰個所謂誒。
修例上有啊毛萬正議員個動議啦，噉係誒，我諗在座嘅人有冇咩邊個需要發言或者需要有意見？因為我似乎都係比較straightforward一個一個motion嚟嘅。係。
O.K.誒喺我哋誒處理緊嗰啲落廚食嘅情情況下咧，就或者請政府嘅代表誒李女士咧，有冇誒公署副署長有冇需要扼要咁剛才嗰一節嘅意見咧，就好簡單咁發言啊。
for ethnic minorities with personalised case management, intensive vocational counselling and follow-up, as well as tailor-made strategies to enhance ethnic minority employability.
係，咁當然我哋今日收到依啲意見咧，我都會我哋都會轉交翻嚇相關嗰個誒局咧，佢去去考慮嘅。係，亦都希望你將我哋誒有委員嘅意見咧，需要就有關嘅五億元嘅洗費嘅詳情咧，有如果有文件提供我哋嘅話，希望我哋下次或者適當時候可以處理好嘛。唔該曬李女士。
job seekers and disable with disabilities. Of course, EM job seekers are not disabled, but we have certain disadvantages comparative to the Chinese counterparts, such as language barrier, culture sensitivity. Some may have lack of effective communication skills and certain employers stereotype attitude, which needs to
因損失或麻煩的背後，這是很重要的，讓無業人士找到工作。或讓無業人士找到工作，或讓
個案工作者係至為重要，對EM職業尋求者而言，他促進了EM職業尋求者與僱主之間的初步聯繫，以便於促進有效的溝通，並打斷某些僱主的刻板印象。僱員部要求我們為殘疾人士提供服務。
division 建，就失業、能力、無職、尋職者，可全員或兼職工作，提供服務。此division 有兩大益處。一方面，它將提供就業機會，並跟進案件。另外，它將提供就業機會及訓練課程的補助，以及就業機會及訓練課程的補助。
財產會領取；，另一側，則是提供農民和牧民的教育和訓練，並幫助他們獲得工作機會。這將改善他們的經濟狀況，並提高他們的社會地位。
我要求政府提供支援，我要求政府提供支援。
誒，今日第一節嘅發言時間誒，發言嘅人士完結啦。但係我哋睇翻時間咧，已經五十五分，應該就第一節完嘅。噉啊，手頭上咧有蒙民正議員嘅一個動議嘅，就另外當然係有需要誒，政府嘅代表或者要加入嘅發言啦，以及誒委員誒問題啦。但係時間上似乎真係比較急嘅。噉我。
咩所謂employment employment centre咧？我想我所謂，我想你聽埋我份先，唔好咁介意衝動住。同我哋衝動啫嘛！你二零一七一一七年二月十三號咧，我哋有個動議通過咗嘅咧，就係話想勞工處設立一個少數族裔嘅就業科咧。我想瞭解下你嗰個意見咧，同之前嗰個就業科咧係。
是否等同定還是係類似定還是係唔同嘅事幹呢？如果係嘅話，我哋或者如果係通過咗一次，我哋有冇需要再次通過呢？定還是你覺得堅持今次需要處理呢個動議呢？我insist that this should go through the committee. Fine, fair enough. That's fine. Please, because I'm doing it on behalf of an.
唔該，你先。好多謝主席啊。咁剛才我哋好多謝咧，係總共係有廿二位誒出席今日誒會議嘅誒團體嘅代表啦，或者人士啦，係畀咗啲意見我哋嚇。咁誒裏邊咧有有啲部分咧就誒同勞工處無關嘅嚇，咁有啲係同勞工處有關，或者有啲係同。
please。
真係通過咗嘅。
what have you?
即係通過嘅啦嚇，誒。
information rolling off your tongues are just not good enough.
啊！通過就通過，通過啦，正式通過。好，得我聽正式通過啦。
This is all contagious, you see. This is a choice of words.
你
Department. That's question one. And question two: Can you not just have counters within the Labour Department, but proper?
有冇人需要發言？如果冇嘅話咧，我哋亦都我諗在座似冇乜人反對嘅，噉我哋都冇冇需要又debate或者再投票啦。我哋就當佢通過咗啦，好嘛？OK，thank you。
跟住咧，我哋誒有四位同事都舉咗手嘅，我對唔住咧，因為我可能時間真係好趕逼，你大家計唔計三分鐘到？啊，有需要嘅話，我哋下一節再補翻好嘛？誒，黃萬正議員啊。
譬如再培訓局啊，或者職業培訓等等嚇。咁誒，因為都都有好多嘢回應我要做啦。咁可能可能喺下一節會方便啲。不過特別有一度咧，求先誒係阿阿劉小姐咧就提到嗰個五億元嗰個誒嗰個嗰嗰個嗰個嗰個基金嚇嗰個設立嘅。有多位議講。
都都有提到噉，係啦，係啦嚇。咁呢度咧，因為呢個係誒的，而且確咧就唔係勞工處嗰個工作範疇。不過我可以畀少少資料啊，噉我可以精簡啲嘅嚇。咁因為咧就誒誒誒政府咧就將會成立一個跨局跨部門嘅督導委員會嚇，噉就由政務司司長咧出任主。
主席負責去統籌、檢視同埋監察咧，有關於係呢個支援少數族裔人士嘅工作。咁至於誒政府預留嗰五億元嚇，點樣可以去加強到為少數族裔嗰個人士提供嘅支援咧，就會由呢個督導委員會詳細會去考慮嘅。
係，我揾正議員。誒，我，
經過yet another déjà vu episode， it's all very familiar， right？ And I need to tell you， our labour and welfare chief， Dr C K Law， apparently， not apparently， I actually saw it。
Only day before yesterday, he said something like, "Oh, in Hong Kong, for ethnic minority services, we have specialised service counters offering job referrals and simultaneous interpretation, personalised career consultancy."
I mean, it's all good on paper, as some of you were saying. It only exists on paper, or maybe only in the cyber world. It's not working. Now, please, can Hong Kong government officials just? Can can I urge you to be just a bit more genuine?
cosmic joke on the entire community. Oh, you haven't been doing much or enough, and you say, oh, we have done a lot. Thank you very much. And that's the end of the conversation, the dialogue. It's completely meaningless, right? This supposed persuasively glib kind.
Question one: Your so-called ambassadors—I do mean so-called ambassadors—who are just good for six months only, could you not make them just a bit more permanent, please? Make it a standing kind of post within the Labour.
please。
ethnic minority job seeking centres。
晨會都傾向嗰個方向做，但係小組又係冇嘅。我就希望呢度答一答政府有冇噉嘅政策傾向，話嚟緊具體點樣操作，作為一個以身作則。唔該，主席，留分鐘畀佢。好啊，副主席唔該。
誒，你哋有冇即時嘅回應關於permanent同埋嗰個centre instead of counters啊？好多謝主席嚇。咁誒兩方面先啦嚇。第一方面咧就係我哋嗰個誒少數族裔嘅服務大事嚇。其實依個誒項目咧，我哋一路持續咧係進行嘅，持續係做嘅，就唔係一個短。
網站嘅項目嚟㗎。咁至於話咧，嗰啲誒父母大使，They don't seem to be achieving much, didn't you hear? They're just they're staging a front. Oh, the government's doing something. We have ethnic minority-looking people looking after you. Aren't you satisfied?
by now，this is just this is complete lack of sincerity。併完咗，有時間我再畀你補翻答好嘛？唔該你。誒，温兆堅議員，唔該。多謝席。時間所限，有啲背景都真係要省略啦。我簡單咁講就，首先嗰個消逐瑞喺香港嗰個狀況就真係唔理想，大家都知。咁正話有朋友提到。
咧誒嗰個誒佢哋就業狀況咁個數據咧就係誒其實香港非技術工人大約係兩成到啦，即係佔咗整體人口十九點五個percent，但係喺消數族業入邊咧，非技術工人個比例咧去到七十五點八嘅。咁呢個數據就誒數字可説話啦，即係佢面對一個點樣？
嘅誒社會流動機會或者工作機會噉，當然呢個誒結果係綜合嘅結果，就係佢哋面對喺一個唔公平狀態之後達至嘅綜合結果，包括誒學習中文嘅機會、學誒讀書嘅機會、向上流動等等機會。噉就我覺得有啲嘢政府可以做得好啲。剛才毛孟靜講咗個點。
誒嗰個就業支援中心，我覺得可以做得好啲，因為事實上誒而家張建中誒司長將會領導嗰個五億元啦。我到時講我哋我哋特首講，我哋香港乜都缺，可能啊最唔缺係錢㗎嘛。噉我就我就唔知點解出手咁低，即係五億元，即係極之低。跟住佢做個範圍咁大喎，係整體個。
仲要係噉，我就諗唔到，我哋只係講嗰啲咁綜合嘅結構性嘅，包括黃就業啊、讀書啊、學中文等等嘅各種嘅範疇，佢點樣投依五億元咧，可以五餅二餘咁做到嘢？噉我個問題好簡單，主席誒，第一就係剛才好多團體都提及嗰個工商率咧，咁呢個亦都係事實。我睇翻。
資料就譬如理工大學啊，陳炳全教授都做過調查，就係喺地盤嗰個工商比例咧，少數族裔人士係比起本地工人高三三成嘅。噉我想問勞工處喺呢方面有啲咩可以做？喺無論喺翻譯或者資訊上提供教育方面。第二咧就係誒，就住剛才講到誒，勞工處會唔會？
會主動地去到協嚟聯絡一啲僱主，嘗試去誒揾多啲就業機會畀佢哋。其中一個都可以做嘅，政府自己可以做嘅，就係以身作則。嗱，依個政府做得好差，無論喺殘疾人士，以至係少少俗語嘅聘用入邊。雖然嗱殘疾人士好少少，佢誒冇法例亦都冇指引，不過佢自負部門都有啲心領。
啊！主席嚇，誒三方面啦，誒工商方面先嚇。誒勞工處咧喺就住少數族裔人士喺職業安全同埋健康方面咧係有做好多功夫嘅嚇。好似譬如我哋啲誒有關我哋誒教啲少數族裔人士嚇點樣注意職業安全啊，喺唔同嘅譬如建造業啊、高空工作啊或者其他嘅。
行業裏邊，我哋呢啲宣傳單張或者小冊子咧，係有包括用少數族裔嘅母語去印製嘅。咁譬如以公誒呢個建築地盤為例啦，我哋同工會啊、同商會啊嘅去合作，亦都同呢個職安局去合作咧。我哋係喺地盤有啲五間安全講座嘅，係咧。
係向啲小數族裔咧工人咧係推介有關嘅嘅資料。咁另外其他譬如回誒巡迴展覽啊、講座啊，喺小數族裔週報裏面等等呢啲工作，噉我唔詳細講啦。咁第二方面咧係關於話誒嗰個誒誒五億元方面啦嚇，咁呢個頭先我都講咗，呢個唔係我哋勞工處嗰個公。
工作嗰個範疇，我哋可以咧係將有翻嘅意見咧係轉介翻去畀誒誒相關嘅政策局。咁第三方面咧就話啊，我哋勞工處有冇主動去咧幫一啲少數族裔咧，我哋盡量去揾一啲工set up嚟做嚇。依個主席我哋係有做嘅，一路有做。咁亦都同埋我想有一點想講出就。
都講咗好多年。
啊！
但係講咗咁多年之後咧。
好，請張超紅議員。
反映到個問題咯，啊唔該，主席。
我想問政府，究竟知唔知道香港嘅少數族裔佢哋嘅失業率係幾多咧？
主席，即係最新嗰個扶貧嘅少數族裔嘅貧窮報告咧，都顯示。
可唔可以答一答失業率啊？你哋社有冇數字喺度咧？啊，好啊，主席，我請我同事阿許處長嚇提供有關嘅資料。
誒多謝主席。根據二零一六年嘅中期人口報告咧，誒少數族裔人士嘅失業率咧就誒，如果整體少數族裔嚟講咧，就係。
剛才亦都有不少嘅團體都話咧，就話啊，因為咧嗰啲誒唔識唔識得中文啦，咁所以喺工喺揾工方面咧嗰個困難。其實咧，我哋勞工處，我哋喺幫啲僱主去做招聘嘅活動嘅時候咧，我哋特別係提醒啲僱主，儘量咧係降低嚇對中文嗰個要求，書寫又好。
閲讀又好，誒講嘢都好嚇。咁以一個我哋用翻舊年嘅，以零一七年嘅例子為例啦，我哋勞工處我哋處理嘅，我哋負責去做招聘嘅誒嘅職位空缺咧，誒五個僱主話佢唔需要誒嗰個求職者咧係有粵粵語嘅繪畫能力，係唔需要。
嘅話咧係有超過九萬份工，誒唔需要中文閲讀，唔需要中文書寫能力咧，亦都咧一樣係有超過九萬份嘅工作嘅空缺㗎。主席，我我補補嗰句啫，即係誒呢啲資料我我哋確認嘅，我我唔阻你太多時間，我啲時間好好有限，我畀我畀咗十十零秒我得㗎。誒，我哋知嘅，亦都賺水路。
公署真係有聽過呢啲工作去做嘅，但係咧，我哋其實我覺得今日好為為難咗佢哋。其實咧，我問個問題又是後邊嗰個咧，就係政府大政策嘅，我都係需要咧民政事務局甚至嚟緊政務司司長辦公室要揾同事嚟嘅。我希望係提呢點啫。如果唔係咧，即係我哋石頭撞唔出血嘅噉。佢搭咗勞工處，我都知佢有做嘅嘢，但係唔會。
誒少少續鋭係嗰個貧窮率係升咗嘅，即係無論係政策介入前或者介入後咧都升咗。咁呢個二零一一到二零一六嘅變化咧令人擔憂。咁當然我哋好多謝咁多位團體嚟到，誒咁多位朋友嚟到講，即係少少就業就業嘅困難之處啦。咁呢個我哋。
三點七個百分之三點七，依個係二零一六年嘅。咁如果當年呢個係講，亦都係扣除咗呢一個誒誒外籍家庭傭工嘅少數族人士誒。你計埋嗰啲即係外籍啊，白種人啊嗰啲，或者我我再可以再詳細。好啊，你請你淨係講緊南亞裔嗰部分。南亞嗱當誒，或者我講翻當年。
然香港，如果扣除咗誒外籍家庭用工嘅時候，整體嘅失業率咧，其實都係三點七嘅percent嘅啊，百分之三點七啦。咁如果淨係南亞裔嚟講咧，係百分之五點三嘅啊，係比起整體係高一啲嘅啊。噉啊，如果你話再去再細分嘅話咧，就會係印度人就百分之二點五點二啦。
啊，係主張答啦，李女士。
喺少數族裔呢部分咧，幫助佢哋就業咧。
一年數字有冇咧？如果冇嘅話，係咪可以提供？
查得到個數，不過我哋可以係會後翻去試下嘅。唔該，主席。
P.I.你係咪應該幾多年內將嗰個比例咧提升到幾多噉樣咧？
啦，啊巴基斯坦人就百分之九點二啦，尼泊爾人咧係百分之四點一嘅。
資料跟住自己揾工嗰啲啦，咁呢啲人你係專門幫佢揾工嘅，個成功率咧係單位數字嘅百分之單位數字。有冇呢方面嘅數字咧？係啦，呢呢個係誒你哋自己提供出嚟嘅資訊，噉你你話唔承認呢個數字？
誒，張賢係好誒，最後啦，即係嗱，我哋睇到誒勞工處幫助少少族裔就業嗰個成功率咧，係相當低嘅，即係講緊誒早幾年六點幾，而家好似七點五咁上下啦，百一百分之七點五。
係張毅誒咁呢個息率咧，就即係都南亞瑞嗰邊咧，都係明顯高過我哋整體嘅香港息率嘅。噉我想問，即係對於政府嚟講，呢一個係咪一個值得關注嘅地方，同埋係咪應該有相應增加嘅資源咧，去投放喺？
誒主席，如果喺勞工處方面嚟講咧，我哋喺誒就業方面咧，我哋係有特別咧，係誒針對南亞裔人士，譬如好似我哋，不如噉啊，主席誒，你畀一個金額喎，你究竟擺咗幾多錢額外嘅係專針對幫助少數族裔嘅？
誒主席，我而家手頭上冇數字，究竟可唔可以去做到呢個數字出嚟咧？因為我哋嘅服務，我哋一係一行常嘅服務嚟嘅。譬如好似啊，我哋做宣傳推廣，我哋譬如話啊喺僱傭權益方面嚇，我哋所有嘅僱員啦，當中亦都包括有少數族裔嘅僱員。呢啲係喺計算嘅時候，我哋未必可。
咁呢個係即係低到驚人嘅，就算佢幫殘疾人士揾工咧，都比呢一個咧係高成大概十倍到啦。咁所以呢一個係即係我我唔知道勞工處或者都有個講法，即係點解一個咁極低嘅成功率？誒，你哋有冇個指標，即係或者作為一個K？
啊，李女士，首先你接受呢個數字同埋有冇咩意見回應？誒，主席嚇，首先咧，我手頭上我就唔誒冇話阿阿張議員嗰個數字，因為我要詳細解釋少少嘅嚇，因為咧誒，如果誒我哋喺誒求職服務或者就業服務嚟講咧，我哋誒嘅誒求職人士。
佢第一，佢唔需要一定咧喺勞工處登記嘅，唔需要咁做，因為點解咧？我哋譬如我哋喺網上啊，或者我哋資訊站啊等等，我啲職業職位嘅空缺咧，已經係係係登曬出嚟㗎啦。咁第二咧，我哋而家絕大部分咧，我哋嘅空缺咧，嗰啲僱主咧，係可以喺喺個空缺裏邊咧，係。
提供埋個僱主個聯絡嘅方法，咁於是乎咧，求職人士嚇，無論係少數族裔又好，或者唔係少數族裔都好啦，都可以直接咧係同個僱主係約個見工嘅，唔需要勞工處做一個轉介嘅服務。咁所以根本我手頭上亦都唔會有個數字，就話啊，究竟幾多啊？依啲空缺。
啊，喺喺啲求職人士睇咗勞工處依個資料之後，揾到份工去做嚇，因為唔會唔會有一個咧係話可以分得到，係唔係少數族裔依一個個資料喺度嘅。陳主席，噉你又知道即係有二千幾人嚟揾過你，呢啲係少數族裔嘅，好明顯就唔包括你話自己睇。
五分鐘唔計。
先得㗎，即係幾多人登記咗？
如果你話佢哋係啊經過轉介而獲僱主提出聘任嘅話咧，如果喺二零一七年嚟講咧，總共有一百五十一個小數族裔人士，佢哋係登誒經過轉介服務而僱主提出聘任嘅。
剛才又好似講真係個個率點計啊？或者咁啦，我哋書面上地後補補充咧，數字上我諗佢再比較詳細少少講，可能更加清晰好嘛。噉我哋而家咧就誒唔好意思啦，因為我哋真係遲咗好多啦，我哋休息誒五分鐘，讓我哋秘書同事安排誒再第二節嘅誒公職人士。
啊！主席，容許我補充好嘛？剛才我話咧，我整體嚟講啊，因為好多大絕大部分咧，嗰啲空缺都係可以求職人士直接去揾個僱主去約見工。咁呢啲我唔會掌握得到。究竟呢啲成功嘅個案咧，係少數逐樣定唔係少數逐樣求職人士？好啦，咁至於求先啊張議員去計。
繼續問第二個問題啊！如果係勞工處係提供轉介嘅就業服務嘅時候咧，咁依個咧，我哋係會有我我哋係有數字，關於咧佢係唔係少數族裔嘅人士嚟嘅？如果有需要，我哋而家可以即場去提供呢啲數字。誒，我啊要講講個數字咧，即有幾多percent係真係少數族裔嘅？有幾多？
percent成功率，如果你有記錄嘅話，好啊。噉我請阿許處長講啲數字。多謝主席。嗱，我即係我諗都都頭先阿阿李女士都解釋過啦。呢個唔係一個成功率嚟嘅。啊，因為佢第一，佢登註冊咗登記咗個就業服務咧，佢唔一定係要經我哋轉介嘅。佢登記咗就業服務，呢個我理解啦，唔唔需要轉介我。
經轉介嗰二千幾宗，誒嗰個亦都唔係轉介二千幾，佢係登記咗登就業服務。因為佢喺網上面咧，有啲佢會登記咗就業服務咧，亦都唔係因為佢想要轉介，而係話因為佢登記咗就業服務咧，有啲服務係可以，例如誒佢登記咗之後，佢話啊，我想誒揾某一啲行業嘅工嘅，佢登。
記咗之後咧，我哋係有一個資訊可以誒通過電郵或者其他方法咧，係通知咗佢嘅。佢所以登記服務唔代表佢係要用我哋嘅轉介服務啊。呢個我諗首先要講清，所以我唔可以話啊，住登記咗求職嘅話咧，就等於咧佢係有有用我哋嘅轉介服務係兩兩兩回事嚟嘅啊。如果
咁當中咧就誒，佢有啲係拒絕咗聘任啦嚇。噉就最終咧，如果係少數就業人士經轉介而入職嘅，即係扣除咗頭先一百五十一個係誒僱主提出聘任啦。咁出誒結果有九十四個咧係入咗職嘅。係有需要先再補充咧，我哋時間上唔好意思啊，張議。佢畀個份母。